Finding Aid for Immanuel United Church of Christ (Detroit, Mich.) records, 1894, 1912-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Immanuel United Church of Christ (Detroit, Mich.) records 1894, 1912-1995, 1942-1978
Immanuel United Church of Christ (Detroit, Mich.)
1 oversize film
6 linear feet
97122 Ba 2
Church established by German immigrant workers to Detroit. The congregation was formerly associated with the Evangelical and Reformed Church. Series in the record group include Administrative files, Registers of Services, Historical Materials, records of Church Organizations, Yearly Files, Publications, and Visual Materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This record group (donor no. 8501 ) was the gift of the church and came to the library in July 1997.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
Immanuel United Church of Christ (formerly Evangelical and Reformed) was founded in 1893 by German immigrant workers who came from present-day Poland to the new industrial area of southwestern Detroit, just north of Michigan Avenue near the border with Dearborn. A major proportion of the founding members had left the Lutheran Church in a dispute over belonging to non-church organizations (labor unions and the Masonic Lodge). From the beginning, the church maintained a parochial school to perpetuate the language and beliefs of its members.
The next generation of congregants, born in the United States, did not maintain as strong ties to their German roots. In 1925, the parochial school was discontinued. Almost three years later, the congregation adopted English for its main service and in its record keeping, although it continued to hold some services in German for thirty more years.
In late 1929, the congregation approved building an impressive new church complex, that included a sanctuary, parsonage, and wing for youth activities. Despite the Depression, the debt for construction was retired within fourteen years.
In 1955, the church reached its peak in adult communicants at 942. The following year, construction of Interstate-94 bisected its neighborhood and destroyed many of its parishioners' homes, resulting in the loss of congregants to the suburbs. A decline in membership followed, which proved irreversible despite attempts at revitalization. In 1958, the church discontinued all services in German.
Three years later, the church sponsored a major study in an attempt to reverse the decline, but membership continued to drop, partially as a response to the Detroit riot and subsequent court mandated cross-district school busing within the city. By the late 1970s, the church considered consolidating with three neighboring ethnically German congregations. The members of Immanuel voted against the merger, stating that "as long as we are able to hold our own, we wish to stay as we are, till we can no longer carry on" (text of membership petition).
When the Latino community began expanding north of Michigan Avenue, the church agreed to share its facilities with a Spanish Pentecostal group in an attempt to survive. In 1997, Immanuel Church sold its Detroit sanctuary and moved its remaining membership (about 150 people, many of whom are infirm) to a church in Dearborn. At this writing (1997), Immanuel is undecided about whether to merge with the Dearborn U.C.C congregation.
The records of Immanuel United Church of Christ have been arranged into seven series: Administrative, Register of Services, Historical Materials, Church Organizations, Yearly Files, Publications, and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Immanuel United Church of Christ (Detroit, Mich.); German Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.; United Church of Christ--Michigan--Detroit.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Immanuel United Church of Christ (Detroit, Mich.); Churches--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.
- Administrative
  The Administrative records chronicle the financial and leadership activities of Immanuel U.C.C. from 1912 to 1995, with the bulk falling between 1942 to 1978. The researcher will find a copy of the 1894 church constitution in the Constitution and Bylaws file as well as various later drafts. The first volume of Consistory and Congregational meeting minutes contains the earliest consistent documentation of church decisions and activities, which were recorded in German until mid-1927. Minutes were handwritten until early 1969, after which they were typed, copied, and taped into the journal. The folders in this series include minutes, agendas, and reports that are absent from the bound volumes.
  The church's financial activities and membership levels are available from the formal Financial Reports and Year Book Reports to the parent United Church of Christ. More detailed records of disbursements and income are found in several of the Yearly Files. The church's organizations, for example the Consistory, Board of Education, Ladies' Aid Society, and the Pastor, report on their finances and activities in the Annual Reports to the Membership.
  The Pastors file is an incomplete collection of ten of Immanuel's twelve (non-interim) pastors' hiring, letters of resignation, and correspondence after departure. It also includes documents for Keith Westphal, who was minister of Christian Education from 1966 to 1967.
  Immanuel's self-reflection, as it sought to be responsive to its membership, is evident in the number of surveys it did. In 1961, the church coordinated with their parent organization to do a comprehensive Congregational Analysis. In 1967 and 1973, the leadership conducted surveys of the membership; the responses can be found in the corresponding Yearly Files. The most serious evaluation of the church's relevance came in the late 1970s with the decision whether or not to merge with St. Mark's and Trinity churches (the third, St. Peter's, decided to close rather than merge). The Tri-Church Merger series includes meeting minutes, Immanuel's compiled files pertaining to the three churches (each includes a formal appraisal), and their membership survey and ultimate rejection of the merger.
  - Annual Financial Reports 1933, 1942, 1944-1962 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports to the Membership 1943, 1951, 1963, 1964, 1966-1980, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Congregational Analysis 1961 (Box 1)
  - Constitution and Bylaws (Box 1)
  - Membership Directories 1968-1974, 1977, 1981, 1984-1986, 1989, 1993-1995 (Box 2)
  - Pastors 1923-1992 (Box 2)
  - Tri-Church Merger
    - Tri-Church Meeting Minutes 1975-1978 (Box 2)
      (includes minutes of Consolidation Committee. and Building Committee. meetings)
    - Immanuel Tri-Church documents (Box 2)
    - Immanuel Tri-Church Membership Survey (Box 2)
    - St. Mark's Tri-Church documents (Box 2)
    - Trinity Tri-Church documents (Box 2)
  - United Church of Christ Local Church Year Book Report 1937, 1950-1980, 1995 (Box 2)
- Register of Services (attendance, collection money, etc.)
  The Register of Services series contains volumes and other records that tally attendance at each service (noting whether in German or English) and the money collected from offerings. From here, researchers can trace the changing composition and levels of active membership from 1935 to 1989, roughly.
  - 1935-1980, 1989, 7 folders; 6 volumes (Box 2)
    (lacking February 1949-June 1954 December 1958-1969)
- Historical Materials
  The Anniversary Booklets in the Historical Materials series includes programs commemorating more than a dozen anniversaries, the earliest dating to 1923. Included also are two historical pamphlets; one of the Detroit-area Evangelical and Reformed Churches and one of Immanuel Church (on the occasion of the 100th anniversary), which has members' recollections. The Materials from the Cornerstone are in German; a description of its contents, as recorded upon opening it in 1930, is in the 100th anniversary booklet.
  - Anniversary Booklets (Box 2)
  - Materials from Cornerstone of Original Church Building (Box 2)
- Organizations
  The Church Organizations series includes the minutes of various church committees. The Church Workers minutes, attended by Sunday School workers and perhaps the teachers at the parochial school while it was in existence, are in German from 1921 to May 1923. Further information on these organizations, for example, programs from their events, are in the Yearly Files. The Young People's Society and Senior League split one journal, the latter picking up where the former left off. One journal has minutes in German from 1909 to 1928, but the organization is unidentified.
  - Board of Christian Education minutes
    - 1964-1968 (Box 3)
    - 1969-1974 (Box 3)
  - Choir minutes 1948 (Box 3)
  - Church Workers Meeting minutes
    - 1921-1940 (Box 3)
      (the minutes for 1921-May 1923 in German)
    - 1958-1963 (Box 3)
  - Dorcas Circle Meeting minutes
    - 1967-1970 (Box 3)
    - 1971-1974 (Box 3)
  - Ladies' Aid Society minutes
    - 1961-1976 (Box 3)
    - 1977-1980 (Box 3)
  - Ladies' Aid Society agendas
    - 1968-1989 (Box 3)
  - Men's Aid Society dues 1933-1945 (Box 3)
  - Men's Aid Society minutes
    - 1918-1955, 4 volumes (Box 3)
  - Tabea Women's Guild minutes
    - 1940-May 1948 (Box 3)
    - June 1948-1954 (Box 3)
  - Unidentified 1909-1928 (Box 3)
    (in German)
  - Young People's Society 1921-1924 (Box 4)
    (volume includes Senior League minutes, 1924-1928)
- Yearly Files
  The Yearly Files are essentially unordered scrapbooks of church activities. Some years have second files, which document specific organizations that emerged that year, congregation surveys, and Sunday School Planning Charts. Research into church purchases, such as of the Reardon lot in 1978, and other legal documents, such as parishioners' wills, are also in these files. The researcher will notice that records from 1976 are missing, as are those from 1982 to 1989. When received, the records collection contained notebooks, organized chronologically, of the bulk of documents generated by the church. For ease of access, key documents have been pulled out and compiled into distinct series.
  - 1923-1949 (Box 4)
  - 1950-1959 (Box 4)
  - 1960-1964 (Box 4)
  - 1965-1966 (Box 4)
  - 1967
    - General (Box 4)
    - Our Christian Enlistment, statement and congregation survey (Box 4)
  - 1968
    - General (Box 4)
    - Sunday School Planning Charts (Box 4)
  - 1969
    - General (Box 4)
    - Sunday School Planning Charts (Box 4)
  - 1970
    - General (Box 4)
    - Southwest United Ministry/REACH 1970-1972 (Box 4)
  - 1971 (Box 4)
  - 1972 (Box 4)
  - 1973
    - General (Box 4)
    - Membership Questionnaire (Box 4)
    - Michigan-Livernois Neighborhood Council (Box 4)
  - 1974 (Box 4)
  - 1975 (Box 4)
  - 1977 (Box 5)
  - 1978 (Box 5)
  - 1979
    - General (Box 5)
    - Michigan Avenue Community Organization 1979-1980 (Box 5)
  - 1980 (Box 5)
  - 1981 (Box 5)
  - 1990-1995 (Box 5)
- Publications
  Church Publications include the monthly newsletter Outlook. The latter years of this sub-series are incomplete. The Service Bulletins note the service program, pastor, organist, and altar offerings as well as occasional announcements of hospitalizations, deaths, socials, and community organization meetings.
  - Newsletter: Outlook
    - 1964-1995, 18 folders (Box 5)
      (lacks 1985-1992 1994)
  - Service Bulletins
    - 1936-1995, 21 folders (Box 6)
      (lacks 1981-1988 1990-1992)
- Visual Materials
  Visual Materials include a 1943 photograph of the church altar and two reels of film. The reel in Box 6 features the 1930 cornerstone laying and completed church building. The oversize reel is a series of scenes from the late 1940s to early 1950s, including a congregation picnic, Ladies' Aid Society 60th anniversary dinner, and vacation Bible school presentation.
  - Photograph of Church Altar, 1943 (Box 6)
  - Motion picture of cornerstone laying 1930 (Box 6)
  - Motion picture of various church activities, 1940s-1950s (Reel 1)